Inventory of the Jay Johns Papers 1918-1974
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Jay Johns Papers, 1918-1974.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 74 J64
4,525 items.
Personal and business correspondence of Jay Winston Johns, Jr. (1888-1974), coal industrialist from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, and later an "adopted son" of Virginia, becoming a leader in preserving homes of renowned Virginians.
Phillips Brooks,; Harry Ashby de Butts,; Harry Flood Byrd,; George Washington Parke Custis ,; Albert Gallatin,; Carter Glass,; Mills E. (Mills Edwin) Godwin,; Albertis S. (Albertis Sydney) Harrison,; Daniel Harvey Hill,; Stonewall Jackson,; Jay Johns,; James Jackson Kilpatrick,; Francis Lightfoot Lee,; Mary Randolph Custis Lee,; Richard Henry Lee,; Robert E. (Robert Edward)Lee,; George C. (George Catlett) Marshall,; Morton G. Thalhimer,; William M.(William Munford) Tuck.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 4,507 items, 12/01/1974.
Gift: Acc. no. 80-14; 7/01/1980.
Gift: Acc. no. 83-42; 15 items, 9/01/1983.
Gift: Acc. no. 85-46; 1 item, 10/01/1985.
Gift: 2 items, 2/01/1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
Jay Winston Johns, Jr. was a coal industrialist from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, who moved to Virginia and became a leader in preserving homes of renowned Virginians. He married Helen Lambert (1881-1964). Johns became blind in the late 1950's.
He and his wife owned "Ash Lawn," Albemarle County, Virginia which had been the home of James Monroe and designed by Thomas Jefferson. Johns was founder of the Lee-Jackson Memorial, Inc., a foundation dedicated to preserving the memory of Robert E. Lee, Thomas Jonathan "Stonewall" Jackson and the South's part in the Civil War; and a founder of the Virginia Trust for Historic Preservation, an organization whose main purpose was that of purchasing, restoring, and maintaining for the public, homes of renowned men specifically, the Lee-Fendall House in Alexandria, Virginia.
Johns, himself was a strong Democrat and corresponded with and publicly supported all of the prominent Virginia political figures of his time. He was a spirited supporter of the Virginia Military Institute as a member of the Board of Visitors, and as an honorary member of the Alumni Association; a charter member, and later trustee of the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts; and a member of the Virginia Chapter of the Society of the Cincinnati. He also received an honorary degree from the College of William and Mary in 1967.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains mostly personal and business correspondence of Jay Winston Johns, Jr., including papers of the Atlas Fuel Corporation of New York, New York and Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; Lee-Jackson Memorial, Inc.; the Virginia Trust for Historic Preservation; and "Ash Lawn," now owned by the College of William and Mary.
The correspondence of Johns includes correspondence with Virginia Democratic Party figures such as Albertis S. Harrison, William M. Tuck, Mills Godwin, Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and Carter Glass. Other prominent correspondents are Morton G. Thalhimer, Harry de Butts, James J. Kilpatrick, and George C. Marsall. There are records of social occasions given by Mr. and Mrs. Johns, correspondence relating to her illness and death, and papers relating to his death.
The collection includes a manuscript collection by Johns including original items by Phillip Brooks (1835-1983), George Washington Parke Custis(1781-1857), Albert Gallatin (1761-1849) and D. H. Hill (1821- 1889); as well as typescripts and photocopies of Includes letters written by Thomas Jonathan Jackson, Francis Lightfoot Lee, Mary Custis Lee, Richard Henry Lee, and Robert E. Lee; and materials concerning James Monroe and Ezekial Moses.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection has been organized into ten series. Series 1 contains personal papers; Series 2 contains papers from the Atlas Fuel Corporation; Series 3 contains papers from Lee-Jackson, Inc.; Series 4 contains papers from the Virginia Trust for Historical Preservation; Series 5 contains miscellaneous materials; Series 6 contains miscellaneous interests; Series 7 contains papers pertaining to Ash Lawn; Series 8 contains the manuscript collection; Series 9 contains manuscript volumes and other miscellany; and Series 10 contains oversized material.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into series with multiple subseries. The subseries, for the most part, have been arranged alphabetically by persons last name or by subject and then further ordered chronologically by date. Additional descriptions concerning the arrangement of specific subseries can be determined at the subseries level.
Additional Descriptive Data
Related Material
This collection of James Monroe Papers was donated by Jay Johns and includes Includes letters by, to and concerning James Monroe, as well as a few printed items.
Jay Johns Collection of James Monroe Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Jay Johns Collection of James Monroe Papers, 1780-1834. 84 items. Mss. 68 M75
Index Terms
Persons:
Brooks, Phillips, 1835-1893.; de Butts, Harry Ashby, 1895-; Byrd, Harry Flood, 1887-1966.; Custis, George Washington Parke, 1781-1857.; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849.; Glass, Carter, 1858- 1946.; Godwin, Mills E. (Mills Edwin), 1914-; Harrison, Albertis S. (Albertis Sydney), 1907-; Hill, Daniel Harvey, 1821-1889.; Jackson, Stonewall, 1824-1863.; Johns, Helen Lambert, 1881-1964.; Kilpatrick, James Jackson, 1920-; Lee, Francis Lightfoot, 1734-1797.; Lee, Mary Randolph Custis, 1806-1873.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732- 1794.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880- 1959.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831.; Moses, Ezekial.; Thalhimer, Morton G.; Tuck, William M. (William Munford), 1896-1983.
Subjects:
Ash Lawn (Virginia: Estate)
Corporate Names:
Atlas Fuel Corporation (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Lee-Jackson Memorial, Inc.; Virginia Trust for Historic Preservation.
Components List
  Series 1: Personal Papers
- Personal Papers, 1930-1974, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  For additional material relating to this series see Series 10: Oversized Material located at the end of the collection.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1930-1974, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1-13)
    - Personal correspondence, 1930-1935., 44 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Personal correspondence, 1936-1940., 37 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Personal correspondence, 1941-1950., 43 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Personal correspondence, 1951-1955., 36 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Personal correspondence, 1956-1960., 42 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Personal correspondence, 1961-1965., 42 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Personal correspondence, 1966-1969., 69 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Personal correspondence, 1970., 41 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Personal correspondence, 1971., 30 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Personal correspondence, 1972., 51 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Personal correspondence, 1973., 25 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Personal correspondence, 1974., 63 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Personal correspondence, n.d., 25 items (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Correspondence of Social Occasions, 1965-1973, n.d. (Box 1-2)
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    - VMI-UVA Breakfast, 1965 October 9, 22 items. (Box-folder 1:14)
    - State dinner honoring in-coming and going distinguished Virginians, 1966 January 11., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Dinner honoring distinguished Virginians, 1972 January 10., 74 items. (Box-folder 1:16)
      Includes letters A-F.
    - Dinner honoring distinguished Virginians, 1972 January 10., 88 items. (Box-folder 1:17)
      Includes letters G-M.
    - Dinner honoring distinguished Virginians, 1972 January 10., 72 items. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Includes letters N-Z.
    - Miscellaneous material including guest lists, press coverage, and a copy of the invitation, n.d., 33 items. (Box-folder 1:19)
    - VMI-UVA Breakfast, 1972 October 14., 93 items. (Box-folder 1:20)
      Includes letters A-M.
    - VMI-UVA Breakfast, 1972 October 14., 52 items. (Box-folder 1:21)
      Includes letters N-Z and guest list.
    - Dinner honoring Jay Johns, 1973 March 7., 76 items. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Miscellaneous material including copy of invitation, newspaper clippings, program, copy of address, and guest list, n.d., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - VMI-UVA Breakfast, 1973 September 8., 36 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Includes letters A-D.
    - VMI-UVA Breakfast, 1973 September 8., 43 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Includes letters E-L.
    - VMI-UVA Breakfast, 1973 September 8., 33 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Includes letters M-S.
    - VMI-UVA Breakfast, 1973 September 8., 22 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Includes letters T-Z.
    - Miscellaneous including guest lists and empty envelopes, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Miscellaneous guest lists, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Correspondence concerning the illness and death of Mrs. Johns, 1964. (Box-folder 2:7-17)
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent within each folder
    - Correspondence concerning the illness of Mrs. Johns, 1964., 35 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 48 items. (Box-folder 2:8)
      Includes letters A-B.
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 42 items. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Includes letters C-F.
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 38 items. (Box-folder 2:10)
      Includes letters G-H.
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 34 items. (Box-folder 2:11)
      Includes letters I-L.
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 39 items. (Box-folder 2:12)
      Includes letters M-N.
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 27 items. (Box-folder 2:13)
      Includes letters O-R.
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 34 items. (Box-folder 2:14)
      Includes letters S.
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 32 items. (Box-folder 2:15)
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 10 items. (Box-folder 2:16)
      First names only.
    - Correspondence concerning the death of Mrs. Johns., 78 items. (Box-folder 2:17)
      Miscellaneous calling cards and florists' cards, funeral home visitors book, addresses, and sketch of gravestone; also obituaries.
  - Items concerning the death of Jay Winston Johns., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:18)
    Funeral home register and obituary.
  - Personal Business Papers, 1941-1974, n.d. (Box-folder 2:19-20)
    - Financial matters, 1941-1974, n.d., 24 items. (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Legal matters, 1965-1970 n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 2:20)
  Series 2: Atlas Fuel Corporation
- Atlas Fuel Corporation, 1920-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 2:21-24)
  - Balance Sheets, 1958-1964., 48 items. (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1967., 17 items. (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Legal matters, 1924-1959, n.d., 48 items. (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Minutes, 1920-1953., 19 items. (Box-folder 2:24)
  Series 3: Lee-Jackson, Inc.
- Papers of Lee-Jackson, Inc., 1859-1974, n.d. (Box-folder 3:1-22)
  - Correspondence of Lee-Jackson Inc., 1923-1974, n.d. (Box-folder 3:1-11)
    - Correspondence, 1923-1960., 47 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1962., 30 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
    - Correspondence, 1963., 67 items. (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Correspondence, 1964., 71 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Correspondence, 1965., 51 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Correspondence, 1966., 96 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968., 37 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
    - Correspondence, 1969., 39 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1971, 81 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1974., 38 items. (Box-folder 3:10)
    - Correspondence, n.d., 30 items. (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Printed material. (Box-folder 3:12)
    Items include articles, literature, pamphlets, and newspaper clippings.
  - Business Papers. (Box-folder 3:13-14)
    - Finance, insurance, and taxes., 19 items. (Box-folder 3:13)
    - Legal papers., 6 items. (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Photographs., 28 items. (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Miscellaneous., 63 items. (Box-folder 3:16)
    Items include genealogy, mailing lists, and artifacts.
  - Material concerning "Stonewall" Jackson and the Jackson family, 1852-1895, n.d. (Box-folder 3:17-19a)
    - Printed material about "Stonewall" Jackson., 12 items. (Box-folder 3:17)
    - Typescripts of or about "Stonewall" Jackson., 7 items. AlsS. (Box-folder 3:18)
      - T[homas] J[onathan] ["Stonewall"] Jackson, Lexington, Virginia, to "brother" [Warren Jackson], n.p., 1 September 1859., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:18)
        Discusses Anna's [Morrison Jackson] sickness and search for medical treatment from Dr. Watkins of Prince Edward County, Virginia.
      - T[homas] J[onathan] ["Stonewall"] Jackson, Mount Jackson, Virginia, to Colonel Bassett French, Aide-de Camp to Governor of Virginia, n.p., 21 March 1862., 1 page. Pst Tcy of ads. (Box-folder 3:18)
        Requests that Colonel French ask the Governor [of Virginia] to order 3,000 muskets; discusses those opposed to war and how he plans to give them departmental jobs. Including Pst Tcy of ads, 21 March 1862, from T[homas] J[onathan] ["Stonewall"] Jackson, Mount Jackson, Virginia, to Colonel and Basset French, n.p., discussing the use of bayonets when firearms cannot be supplied. 1 page. Including endorsement signed by S. Bassett French, stating that he referred information to General [Robert E.] Lee.
      - T[homas] J[onathan] ["Stonewall"] Jackson, Gordonsville, [Virginia], to "Doctor," Rev. W[illia]m S. White, D. D., Lexington, Virginia, 20 June 1862., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:18)
        Discusses securing an army appointment for Mr. Goul [?]; requests that everyone pray to God for a blessing of "their" [the South's] cause.
      - T[homas] J[onathan] ["Stonewall"] Jackson, Bristow, [Virginia], to General J. R. Trimble, n.p., 29 August 1862., 1 page. Tcy of ads. (Box-folder 3:18)
        Praising him for success and promoting him by offering him two new Regiments.
      - T[homas] J[onathan] ["Stonewall"] Jackson, Lt. Gen[era]l, [near Chancellorsville, Virginia,] to Gen[era]l R[obert] E. Lee, n.p., 2 May 1863., 1 page. TCY of ads. (Box-folder 3:18)
        States plans to attack enemy at Chancellorsville, [Virginia] as soon as possible.
    - Includes letters concerning the Jackson family, 1852-1895, n.d., 7 items. Cys of AlsS. (Box-folder 3:19a)
      - Margaret Junkin [sister-in-law of "Stonewall" Jackson], Lexington, Virginia, to Sartain, n.p., 12 February [18]52., 4 pages. XCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:19a)
        Requests that he publish more of her literary works in the Sartain magazine.
      - Start W[illiam] Arnold, Department of the Interior Washington, D.C., to "Mother" [Laura Ann Arnold], n.p., 31 August 1866., 1 page. XCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:19a)
        Encloses twenty-five dollars for her.
      - Stark [William Arnold], Washington, D.C., to "Mother" [Laura Ann Arnold], Beverly, West Virginia, 28 August 1868., 1 page. XCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:19a)
        Wants to meet her in Grafton, [Virginia], and go to Springfield, [Virginia], together.
      - [Anna "Grace" (Arnold) Evans], Washington, D.C., to "Mother," Laura A[nn] Arnold, Beverly, West Virginia, 17 July 1870., 1 page. XCy of ads. Incomplete. (Box-folder 3:19a)
        Discusses weather and encloses Col. Clarke's bill.
      - M[ary] Anna Jackson, Lexington, Virginia, to John Dimitry, n.p., 8 September 1877., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:19a)
        Thanks him for tribute to the memory of her husband.
      - Stark W[illiam] Arnold, Friendship, Allegany County, New York, to "Mother" [Laura Ann Arnold], n.p., 23 August 1895., 2 pages. XCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:19a)
        Discusses financial situation and interest on Roaring Creek, [Pennsylvania].
      - Margaret Junkin [sister-in-law of "Stonewall" Jackson], Lexington, Virginia, to Sartain [?], n.p. 14 January [?]., 4 pages. XCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:19a)
        Wants to include some of her literary work in his magazine Sartain.
  - Material concerning Robert E. Lee and the Lee family, 1778-1894, n.d. (Box-folder 3:19-22)
    - Printed material and prints about Robert E. Lee., 32 items. (Box-folder 3:19)
    - Correspondence of Robert E. Lee, 1863-1865., 26 items. Cys of AlsS. (Box-folder 3:20)
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Virginia], to "Rob" [Robert E. Lee, Jr.], n.p., 22 July 1863., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        States that his daughter, Agnes, is sick and must go to the doctor; family news.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, Richmond, [Virginia], to Miss Markie C. Williams, n.p., 20 June [18]65., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Discusses his wife's illness; family news; says that he has done "nothing wrong [referring to his indictment for treason] and cannot flee."
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Virginia], to Mr. L. R. Spilman, Att[orne]y at Law, n.p., 10 July [18]65., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Discusses the estate of the late George Washington Parke Custis.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Virginia], to Hon. Reverdy Johnson, Baltimore, Maryland, 27 July 1865., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Expresses thanks for the offering of his professional services concerning the indictment; talks about General Grant's letter that was sent to him.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Virginia], to Mr. W[illia]m D. Cabell, n.p., 27 July [18]65., 2 pages. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Discusses imprisonment of Mr. McCue's son.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, [near Cartersville, Virginia], to Mr. John B. Cocke, n.p., 28 July [18]65., 1 page. TCy of ads. Including XCy of ads. 3 pages. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Thanks him for taking care of his horse; daughter Agnes is still confined.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, [near Cartersville, Virginia], to Miss Norvell Caskie, "Derwent," [Virginia], 29 July 1865., 1 page. TCy of L. Incomplete. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Reports that Anna Logan arrived in buggy by Capt. Owens; met Capt. Bridges at Belmead.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Virginia], to Mrs. Caroline Benson, n.p., 29 July [18]65., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        States that he is enclosing lock of hair and photograph [of himself].
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Virginia], to his son Fitzhugh [Lee], 29 July 1865. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Discusses issue of his war indictments.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County, of Virginia], to Col. Walter H. Taylor, n.p., 31 July 1865., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Requests information to recognize "bravery and devotion of the Army of Northern Virginia."
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County, Virginia], to Col. Rich[ar]d S. Maury, n.p., 31 July [18]65., 2 pages. XCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Talks about suffering of the people of the South and his concern for their welfare.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County, Virginia], to General [Wade Hampton], n.p., 1 August 1865., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Gives details of his last battle at Appomattox Court H[ouse], [Virginia].
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County, Virginia], to "Brother Carter" [Carter C. Lee], n.p., 18 August [18]65., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Family news; discusses possible profits from publication of his works.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County, Virginia], to W[illia]m D. Cabell, Richmond, [Virginia], 21 August [18]65., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Regrets that he is too old to take charge of Mr. Cabell's farm.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville. [Cumberland County, Virginia], to "Bertus" [Robert E. Lee, Jr.], n.p., 21 August 1865., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Sorry to hear of his son's sickness; much family news.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, Powhatan County, Virginia, to "Gentlemen" [Messrs. John W. Brockenbourgh[sic], Rector, S. McD. Reid, Alfred Leyburn, Horatio Thompson, D. D., Bolivar Christian, T. J. Kirkpatrick, Committee], Washington College, [Lexington, Virginia], 24 August 1865., 1 page. TCy of LS. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Regrets that he feels he cannot accept the position of president of Washington College.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County], Virginia, to Rev[eren]d Philip Slaughter, n.p., 26 August 1865., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Endorses General Long's statements "in favour of your young kinsman."
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County], Virginia, to Hon. John Letcher, Lexington, Virginia, 28 August 1865., 1 page. TCy of LS. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Express strong feelings about union of the people in an effort to restore peace; has been offered presidency at Washington College.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County, Virginia], to REv[eren]d Philip Slaughter, n.p., 31 August [18]65., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County], Virginia, to A. M. Kelley, Petersburg, Virginia, 4 September 1865., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Declines job proposition with regret.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County], Virginia, to Count Joannes, City of New York, [New York], 4 September 1865., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Expresses gratitude for the offering of legal services if he is tried for treason.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County], Virginia, to Captain Josiah Tatnall, Savannah, Georgia, 7 September 1865., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        States positive attitude about everyone aiding the country in its restoration.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, Virginia, to "Captain" [Capt. Matthew Fontaine Maury, Mexico], 8 September [18]65., 1 page. TCy of LS. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Rejects Maury's idea of starting a new country in Mexico in order to fight for the United States' restoration; asks that Maury stay in Virginia and help in the restoration.
      - Mrs. Robert E. Lee [Mary (Custis) Lee], n.p., to "Miss Em" [Miss Emily Mason], "Derwent," [Virginia], 10 September 1865., 1 page. TCy of AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Refers to Mrs. [Jefferson] Davis living in Augusta, Georgia; says that Mrs. Davis knows nothing of her husband and that the curfew is strict for everyone, white and black.
      - R[obert] E. Lee, near Cartersville, [Cumberland County, Virginia], to Col. Rich[ar]d. S. Maury, n.p., 11 September [18]65., 1 page. TCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:20)
        Refers to Colonel Maury's father's plans in Mexico.
    - Printed Material about the Lee Family., 7 items. (Box-folder 3:21)
    - Material concerning the Lee Family, 1778-1894, n.d., 22 items. Cys of ALsS. (Box-folder 3:22)
      - Richard Henry Lee, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to Patrick Henry, esquire, Governor of Virginia, Williamsburg, [Virginia], 21 October 1778., 1 page. XCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:22)
        Discusses financial situation concerning payment of Continental troops and others.
      - Francis Lightfoot Lee, Richmond, [Virginia], to "dearest" [?], n.p., 5 July 1780., 2 pages. XCy of ads. (Box-folder 3:22)
        Discusses developments in Virginia concerning the arrival of the French fleet; family news.